Register of the Rusztem Vambéry Papers, 1887-1948
Hoover Institution Archives
Rusztem Vambéry Papers,
1887-1948
75089
Vambéry, Rusztem, 1872-
Number of Containers: 9 manuscript boxes (3.75 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, speeches and writings, reports, and printed matter, relating to criminology, Hungarian domestic and foreign affairs, Hungarian- American relations, and Hungarian emigres in the U.S.
Administrative Information
Access
The collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1975.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Crime and criminals; Hungarians--United States; Hungary; Hungary--Foreign relations--United States; Hungary--Politics and government; United States--Foreign relations; United States--Foreign relations--Hungary; Diplomats--Hungary
Biographical Note
Rusztem Vambéry, 1872-1948
1872 Born, Budapest, Hungary
1897 Admitted to the Bar of Budapest
1899-1913 Judge to the Court of Appeals and attached to the Department of Bill Drafting at the Ministry of Justice
1902 Reader in criminal law, Law School at the University of Budapest
1905 Secretary of Juridical Society
1908-1921 Professor of Law, Law School at the University of Budapest
1913-1939 Editor, Jogtudományi Koezloeny (Law Gazette)
1914 Vice Chairman of the liberal Kossuth Party
1918 Member of the National Council during th October Revolution
1922-1938 Practiced law (defended Mátyás Rákosi and other political prisoners of the left, lectured in Hungary, Czechoslovakia and England)
1924-1939 Founder and editor in chief of Századunk (Our Century, a journal of sociology)
1938 Immigrated to the United States of America
1939-? Professor at the New School of Social Research, in New York
1939- President of Committee for New Democratic Hungary
1941?-1945 Special Advisor to the U.S. Office of Strategic Services (OSS) and the British Information Service on Hungarian matters
1946-1948 Envoy Extraordinary and Minister Plenipotentiary to the United States (appointed September 6, 1946 and resigned May 19, 1948)
Container List
- Biographical File, 1897-1948. (Box 1)
  Personal documents, doctor's diploma, biographical data, personal data sheets, recommendations, and newspaper clippings, arranged chronologically.
- Correspondence, 1890-1948 (Box 1-2)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
  - Unidentified, 1938-1948 (Box 1)
  - Alexander, Abraham (Princeton, New Jersey), 1938 (Box 1)
  - Abraham, Dezsoe (Budapest, Hungary), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Alth, (first name not given) (Connecticut), 1948 (Box 1)
  - American Guild for German Cultural Freedom, Inc. (New York), 1941 (Box 1)
  - American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee, Inc. (New York), 1943 (Box 1)
  - Auer, Pál (Budapest, Hungary), 1945 (Box 1)
  - Aufbau/Reconstruction (New York), 1947 (Box 1)
  - Bán, Antal (Zuerich), 1947 (Box 1)
  - Benn, Captain (first name not given) (n.p.), 1922 (Box 1)
  - Boehm, Paul (Solna, Sweden), 1948 (Box 1)
  - British Embassy (Washington, D. C.), 1947 (Box 1)
  - British Information Service (New York), 1941-1946 (Box 1)
  - British Liaison Office with the United Nations (New York), 1943-1945 (Box 1)
  - British Political Representative (Bucharest, Romania), 1946 (Box 1)
  - Carp, Betty (New York), 1942 (Box 1)
  - Carr, E. H. (London), 1947 (Box 1)
  - Chicago Daily News (Chicago), 1939 (Box 1)
  - Clark, Tom C., Attorney General (Washington, D. C.), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Columbia Broadcasting System (New York), 1943 (Box 1)
  - Columbia University (New York), 1940 (Box 1)
  - Commentary, a Jewish Review (New York), 1946 (Box 1)
  - Coudenhove-Kalergi, Count Richard N. (New York), 1942 (Box 1)
  - Crosby, Helen (New York), 1943 (Box 1)
  - Csornoky, Viktor (Budapest, Hungary), 1946 (Box 1)
  - Czechoslovak Consul General (New York), 1945 (Box 1)
  - Czechoslovak Legation (Washington, D. C.), 1939 (Box 1)
  - Czechoslovak Minister (Washington, D. C.), n.d. (Box 1)
  - Desmond, Thomas C. (Albany, N. Y.), 1946 (Box 1)
  - Faludi, Gyoergy (n.p.), n.d. (Box 1)
  - Finzi, Marcello (New York), 1941 (Box 1)
  - Flexner, Abraham (Princeton, New Jersey), 1939 (Box 1)
  - Foreign Economic Administration (Washington, D. C.), 1944 (Box 1)
  - Fry, Varian (New York), 1940 (Box 1)
  - Fueloep-Miller, Rene (Croton-on-Hudson, New York), 1941 (Box 1)
  - Gavrilovic, Stojan (New York), 1944 (Box 1)
  - Graustein and Kormendi (New York), 1946 (Box 1)
  - Greenbaum, Wolf and Ernst (New York), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Haász, Istvánné and Sváb, Miklósné (Budapest, Hungary), 1945 (Box 1)
  - Halasi, Bela (Chicago), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Hall, Donald (New York), 1941-1943 (Box 1)
  - Halmos, Irene (Chicago), 1939 (Box 1)
  - Haraszti, (first name not given) (n.p.), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Harriman, J. Borden, Mrs. (New York), 1945 (Box 1)
  - Henry, Charles (New York), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Howard, Harry N. (Arlington, Virginia), 1946 (Box 1)
  - Hungarian Social-democratic Party, secretariat (Budapest, Hungary), 1939 (Box 1)
  - Hungary, Legation (Washington, D. C.), 1946-1948 (Box 1)
  - Hungary, Ministry of Foreign Affairs (Budapest, Hungary), 1947 (Box 1)
  - International Committee for Political Prisoners (New York), 1938-1941 (Box 1)
  - Irwing, (first name not given) (n.p.), 1890 (Box 1)
  - Jelinek, Vl. (Lake Succes, N. Y.), 1947 (Box 1)
  - Journal of Criminal Law and Criminology (Evanston, Illinois), 1940 (Box 1)
  - Károlyi, Count Mihaly (Paris), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Kepecs, Milton (New York), 1948 (Box 1)
  - Kéthly, Anna (New York), 1946 (Box 1)
  - Kobb, Marian (New York), n.d. (Box 1)
  - Kormendi, Ladislas (New York), 1946 (Box 1)
  - Kosanovic, Sava N. (New York), 1946 (Box 1)
  - Krutch, Joseph Wood (New York), 1943 (Box 1)
  - Labour Party (London), 1939 (Box 2)
  - La Follette, Philip F. (Madison, Wisconsin), 1940 (Box 2)
  - London School of Economics and Political Science (London), 1947 (Box 2)
  - Ludwig, Emil (Pacific Palisades, California), 1942 (Box 2)
  - Marley, Lord (New Court, Middle Temple, E.C.4.), 1938 (Box 2)
  - Masaryk, Jan (London), 1941 (Box 2)
  - Massachusetts League of Women Voters (Boston), 1940 (Box 2)
  - Miller, Herbert A. (Bryn Mawr, Pennsylvania), 1938 (Box 2)
  - Minkoff, J. M. (New York), n.d. (Box 2)
  - Molnár, Erik (Budapest, Hungary), 1948 (Box 2)
  - Montogmery, John Flournoy (Princeton, New Jersey), 1942 (Box 2)
  - National Conference of Christians and Jews, Inc. (Louisville, Kentucky), 1948 (Box 2)
  - New School for Social Research (New York), 1939-1940 (Box 2)
  - New York Public Library (New York), 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - News (New York), 1941 (Box 2)
  - Nógrádi, Béla (Cleveland, Ohio), n.d. (Box 2)
  - PM Daily (New York), 1948 (Box 2)
  - Phillips, Natalie K. (Washington, D. C.), 1948 (Box 2)
  - Reményik, Zs. (New York), 1939 (Box 2)
  - Rockefeller Foundation (New York), 1940-1947 (Box 2)
  - Royal Institute of International Affairs (London), 1947 (Box 2)
  - Ryan, Phillis (Washington, D. C.), 1948 (Box 2)
  - Salvemini, Gaetano (Cambridge, Massachusetts), 1942 (Box 2)
  - Schapiro, J. Salwyn (New York), 1938 (Box 2)
  - Segrave, J. C. (Budapest, Hungary), 1938 (Box 2)
  - Sforza, (first name not given) (Cleveland, Ohio, New York), 1941 (Box 2)
  - Steinmetz, Charles (n.p.), 1940 (Box 2)
  - Stern, J. David (Philadelphia, Ohio), 1941 (Box 2)
  - Stumer, Alfred M. (Copenhagen), 1938 (Box 2)
  - Szent-Iványi, Alexander (Boston, Massachusetts), 1947 (Box 2)
  - Trahan, Marcel (Montreal, Canada), 1944 (Box 2)
  - United Nations (Lake Success, N. Y.), 1947 (Box 2)
  - U.S. Courts, Administrative Officer of (Washington, D. C.), 1942 (Box 2)
  - U.S. Department of State (Washington, D. C.), 1941-1947 (Box 2)
  - U.S. Office of Strategic Services (New York), 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - U.S. Office of War Information (New York), 1941-1944 (Box 2)
  - U.S. Treasury Department (Washington, D. C.), 1942-1943 (Box 2)
  - University of California, Department of History (Berkeley), 1939 (Box 2)
  - University of California, International House (Berkeley), 1939 (Box 2)
  - University of California (Los Angeles), 1940 (Box 2)
  - University of Illinois (Urbana, Illinois), 1942 (Box 2)
  - University of Wisconsin (Madison, Wisconsin), 1942 (Box 2)
  - Vince, Alexander (Chicago), 1941 (Box 2)
  - Wrong, George M. (Toronto, Canada), 1940 (Box 2)
- Speeches and Writings, 1890-1948 (Box 2-8)
  Handwritten and typewritten writings, lectures, speeches, book reviews, and letters to editors, arranged by type of document and thereunder alphabetically by either subject or title.
  - Bibliography (Box 2)
  - Untitled writings (Box 2)
    - Balkans (Box 2)
    - Good and evil (Box 2)
    - Danube Valley, Politics and government (Box 2)
    - Del Vayo (Box 2)
    - Democracy (Box 2)
    - Europe, Politics (Box 2)
    - Fascism (Box 2)
    - Hungary, History (Box 2)
    - Hungary, History, Uprising, 1848-1849 (Box 2)
    - Hungary, History, 20th century (Box 2)
    - Hungary, Politics and government (Box 2)
    - Hungary, Politics and government, 1918-1945 (Box 2)
    - Intellect (Box 2)
    - Jews, Hungary (Box 2)
    - Juvenile delinquency (Box 2)
    - Law (Box 2)
    - Minorities (Box 2)
    - Minorities, Central Europe (Box 2)
    - Philosophy, miscellanea (Box 2)
    - Race awarness (Box 2)
    - Social history (Box 2)
    - Truthfulness and falsehood (Box 2)
  - Titled writings (Box 3)
    - Agrarian problem in Southeastern Europe, extracts from a lecture given at the Philadelphia Ethical Society, typewritten, 1944. (Box 3)
    - Akiket nem érdekel sem Ady sem Ignotus (Those, who are not interested either in Ady, or Ingnotus), draft, in Hungarian, typewritten, n.d. (Box 3)
    - And after Horthy what? a draft of an article for the newspaper Harc (Fight), n.d. (Box 3)
    - Angol boertoen reform (British prison reform), published article, Az Est (Evening), July 11, 1923, in Hungarian. (Box 3)
    - Angol buentetoejog (British criminal law), draft, in Hungarian, handwritten. (Box 3)
    - Angol koezvélemény és a halálbuentetés (British public opinion and the capital punishment), published article, Világ (World), January 20, 1923, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Vambéry Rusztem az angol választások mérlegéroel (Rusztem Vambéry, about the election results of England), published article, Világ (World), November 15, 1924, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Apai oeroekségem; Deák Ferenc (Paternal heritage; Francis Deák), published article, Magyar Forum (Hungarian Forum), July 1943, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 3)
    - Ártatlan vér kiáltása (Scream of the innocent blood), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), August 28, 1927, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Ausnahmsrecht - Ausnahmsgewalt (Exceptional right - exceptional authority), published article, Volksstimme (People's Voice), May 19, 1923, in German., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Aussenpolitik der Labour Party (Foreign policy of the Labour Party), published article, Pester Lloyd (Lloyd of Pest), January 3, 1924, in German., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Balkezes jobboldal (Lefthanded Rightwing), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), December 25, 1936, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Béke útja (Way of peace), published article, Kortárs (Contemporary), November 20, 1929, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Benes és a halálbuentetés (Benes and the capital punishment), published article, Reggel (Morning), n.d., in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Boertoenuegy toerténete (Prison history), unpublished, n.d., in Hungarian, handwritten. (Box 3)
    - Boertoenuegyi koerut Észak-Amerikában (Prison system study trip in North-America), published article, Budapesti Hirlap (Budapest News), October 20, 1910, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Buentetoenovella, I-IV. (Penal code revision), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), May 23, 27, 28, and June 5, 1924, in Hungarian., Clippings. (Box 3)
    - Buentetoejog, II. (Criminal law, II.), published article, Budapest, Grill Károly, 1918, 189 p., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 3)
    - Buentetoejogi visszaesés szabályozása tárgyában; vélemény és tervezet (Repeating in criminal law; opinion and draft), published article, n.d. in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 3)
    - Cena jedinecneho characteru (Standard price characteristics), published article, Lidove Noviny (People's News), September 13, 1937, in Czech., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Cenzura (Censurship), published article, Világ (World), October 13, 1918, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Cimbitorlás (Title abuse), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), December 25, 1935, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Crime, the criminal and society, unpublished, course draft, n.d., handwritten. (Box 3)
    - Criminals and war criminals, published article, Nation, n.d.., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Criminology and behaviorism, published article, The Journal of criminal law and criminology, July-August, 1941, printed copy and original handwritten manuscript. (Box 3)
    - Csak becsueletes amnesztia segíthet! A béke paragrafus a buentetoe novellában, published article, Népszava (People's Voice), June 8, 1924, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Danubian peace, published article, Central European Affairs, April 1, 1943., Printed copy. (Box 3)
    - Dat Galenus opes? published article, Orvosi Napló (Medical Diary), October 25, 1934, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Demokrácia válsága (The crisis in democracy), published article, Kassai Napló (Kassa Diary), n.d., in Hungarian. Clipping. Also in Bácsmegyei Napló (Bács county diary), November 25, 1923, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Demokrácia úgynevezett válsága (The so-called crisis of democracy), published article, in Hungarian, n.d., Printed copy. (Box 3)
    - Dilettáns toerveny faragás (Diletant law making), published article, Kereskedoe Joga (Right of the Merchant), October 15, 1921, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Éles politika és csorba buentetés (Sharp politics and dull punishment), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), June 21, 1925, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Elfogultság (Bias), unpublished, n.d., in Hungarian, typewritten. (Box 3)
    - Elméleti és gyakorlati hazafisag (Theoretical and practical patriotism), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), January 27, 1932, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Oe gyuemoelcseikroel esmeritek meg oeket (You recognize them from their fruits), published, article, Esti Kurir (Evening Courier), December 16, 1923, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Englische Finanzen (English finances), published article, Pester Lloyd (Lloyd of Pest), August 7, 1923, in German., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Enigme hongroise? (Hungarian enigme), published, article, France Amerique (French American), April 16, 1944, in French., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Erkoelcs válsága (Crisis of morale), published article, Est(Evening), August 9, 1923, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Eskuedtszék a másvilágon (Jury in the world beyond), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), December 25, 1925, in Hungarian, Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Europaeische Rivalitaet in Persien und die deutsche Bagdadbahn (European rivalries in Persien and the German Bagdad railroad), published article, Deutsche Rundschau (German review), May 1900., Printed copy. (Box 3)
    - Extradition treaties, Budapest, Atheneum, 1908, 20 p. (Box 3)
    - Fachbildung der Gefaengnisbeamten (Training of prison officials), published article, Oesterreichische Zeitschrift fuer Strafrecht, (Austrain Journal for penal law), 1911, in German., Printed copy. (Box 3)
    - Failure of a mission and mission of a failure, unpublished, n.d., typewritten. (Box 3)
    - Fayer László (László Fayer), published article, Világ (World), December 2, 1922, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Fél-igazságok (Half-truth), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), June 4, 1933, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Feleloeségre kell vonni azokat is, akik a szellemi ekrazitot gyártják (Those too shall be held responsible, who manufacture the intellectual expolsives), published article, Esti Kurir (Evening Courier), January 9, 1924, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Fiatalkoruak buenvádi eljárására vonatkozó kuelfoeldi toervények, toervényjavaslatok és vélemények (Foreign laws, bills and opinions relative to the criminal procedure of juvenile deliquents), published article, Budapest, Franklin, 1911., Printed copy. (Box 3)
    - Foeltámadás (Resurrection), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), April 5, 1935, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - `Free Hungary' Movement in the U.S.; new group against Horthy Regime LIberation from Nazism not enough, published article, Voice of Freedom, December 1941?, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Freihandelskonferenz (Free Trade Conference), published article, Pester Lloyd (Lloyd of Pest), October 16, 1922, in German. (Box 3)
    - Fruits of the Berlin-Budapest marriage, published article, source unknown, n.d., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Gazdasági demokrácia (Economic democracy), published article, Gyoeri Lloyd (Lloyd of Gyoer), May 23, 1926, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 3)
    - Genocide, unpublished, draft, n.d., typewritten. (Box 4)
    - Gondolat bilincsei (Chains of thought), published article, source unknown, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Háboru a jog és az igazság ellen (War against the law and the truth), published article, Világ (World), June 22, 1924, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Háboru és jog, (War and law), Budapest, Franklin, 1933, in Hungarian. Printed copy. Also included in the folder: Háboru és jog (War and law), published, Jogi Napló, May 25, 1933, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Hadifogság (War captivity), published article, Világ (World), December 25, 1914, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Halálbuentetés (Capital punishment), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), February 26, 1928, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Harmadik egyetem (The third university) published article, Szeged és vidéke (Szeged and it's region), December 25, 1906, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Heidelbergi kongresszus (Congress of Heidelberg), published article, source unknown, n.d., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Horogkeresztre feszitett jog (Law, crucified upon the swastika), published article, Ujság (News), June 7, 1934, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - How to fight antisemitism, unpublished, draft, n.d., typewritten. (Box 4)
    - Hungarian problem, New York, 1942, 47 p., published pamphlet. Also included in the folder, book reviews in German and Hungarian., Clippings. (Box 4)
    - Igazi turánizmus diadal (Triumph of genuine Turanism), published article, Esti Kurir (Evening Courier), July 4, 1924, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Igy is lehet Istent szolgálni, (This way too can God be served), published article Népszava (People's Voice), June 25, 1926, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Is liberalism doomed? unpublished, n.d., handwritten. (Box 4)
    - Dr. Isidor Baumgarten, published article, Pester Lloyd (Lloyd of Pest), October 1, 1914, in German., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Jó ember és a rossz ember (Good man and bad man), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), February 22, 1931, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Joevoe boertoenrendszere (Future prisonsystem), Budapest, Pallas, 1914. Published pamphlet, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Jog, forrandalom és népbiróság (Law, revolution and people's court), published article, Bérmunkas naptár (Wage Laborer Calendar), 1947, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Jókai politikai csillaga (Jókai's political star), published speech, Világ (World), February 22, 1925, in Hungarian., Clippings. (Box 4)
    - Jubilálunk (Celebrating our jubilee), published article, Ember (The Man), n.d., in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Kereskedelem és kriminalitás (Commerce and delinquency), published article, unknown, n.d., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Kereskedoe becsuelete (Merchant's honor), published article, source unknown, n.d., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Kereszt (Cross), published article, Világ (World), April 12, 1925, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Két emigrácio (Two emigrations), published article, Tárogató (Clarinet), October 1940, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Koez- és jogrend (Public- and legal order), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), July 19, 1936, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Komor esperes (Stern churchman), published, Népszava (People's Voice), November 13, 1927, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Konstantinápolyi benyomások (Impressions about Constantinople), published article, Ujság (News), November 12, 1916, in Hugarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Kostgeldwucher (Costusury), published article, Pester Lloyd (Lloyd of Pest), March 6, 1923, in German., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - A kriminalistanak nincs oka arra, hogy az utolsó tíz év eredményeire túl bueszke legyen... (The criminalist has no reason to be too proud of the last ten years' achievements), published article, Esti Kurir (Evening Courier), December 25, 1923, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Kriminalpszichologia (Criminalpsychology), published article, Világ (World), December 25, 1913, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Kriminologia (Criminology), published article, source unknown, n.d., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Kukák (Dumbs), published article, Népszava (People's Voice), December 25, 1931, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Kultúra és igazság (Culture and truth), published article, Uj fény (New light), October 1941, in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Labour Party választási kuezdelme (Labour Party's election campaign), published article, Világ (World), October 29, 1924, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Law and legalism, published article, Nation, December 1, 1945., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Law of the tribunal, published article Nation, October 12, 1946., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - `Legesleghatályosabb' ( `Strongest' ), published article Népszava (People's Voice), January 15, 1928, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Levéltitok megsértés? (Letter intercepting?), published article, Posta (Mail), June 15, 1916, in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - `Libro e moschetto...' ( `Book and musket' ), source unknown, n.d., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Lombroso, published article, source unknown, n.d., in Hungarian., Clipping. (Box 4)
    - Madarsko a Ceskoslovensko; staci jen styky hospodarske? (Hungary and Czecholovakia; stops and economic contacts), published article, Democraticki stred (Democratic step)?, 1937, in Czech., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Magyar gyermekvédelem, (Hungarian child care), published article, source unknown, n.d., in Hungarian., Printed copy. (Box 4)
    - Magyarország, Európa és a trianoni béke reviziója (Hungary, Europe and the revision of the Treaty of Trianon), published article, Pesti Naplo (Diary of Pest), December 20, 1927, in Hungarian., Clipping (Box 4)